Guide to the Knute Hill Papers 1909-1963
Washington State University Libraries: Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC)
Knute Hill Papers
1909-1963
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Terrell Library Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 194
Hill, Knute
16 containers. 8 linear feet of shelf space.
Correspondence and printed material relating to Hill's activities as school teacher, administrator, legislator; United States Representative, speaker to secular and religious groups, author of "Letters to the Editor" in diverse newspapers, Indian agency superintendent, Radio Farm Program reporter and commentator, and consulting appraiser for the Columbia Basin Project.
1876 Born, Creston, Illinois
1906 LLB. University of Wisconsin
1908 Lawyer, Eau Clair, Wisconsin Married Helen Jensen, deceased 1936
1911 Teacher, Principal, Superintendent, public schools of Benton County, Washington
1923 Farmer, Lecturer of the Grange
1927 Representative, Washington State Legislature
1933 Elected as a Democrat to the Seventy-third and the four succeeding Congresses (March 4, 1933-January 3, 1943) Member of the House committees on Executive Departments Expenditures, Indian Affairs, Irrigation and Reclamation, and Public Lands.
1943 Superintendent of the Uintah-Ouray Indian Agency, Fort Duchesne, Utah
1944 Farm Reporter and Commentator, KHQ-KGA, Spokane, Washington
1946 Director of Information and Consulting Appraiser, Columbia River Project, Ephrata, Washington
1951 Retired
1963 Died
In a very real sense this collection is one of personal papers insofar as the bulk of the items is concerned with Mr. Hill and his friends without having the status of working papers or office records. The items are those that were meaningful to Mr. Hill over the years and express his selection of the papers he wished to preserve.
Here is correspondence to and from Mr. Hill interfiled and combined with other printed materials used during his tenure as school teacher and administrator, politician, Representative in the Washington State Legislature and in the U.S. Congress, speaker and lecturer to secular and religious audiences, author of "Letters to the Editor" in diverse newspaper, Indian Agency Superintendent, Radio Farm Program reporter and commentator, and Consulting Appraiser for the Columbia River Project.
The collection consists of: Letters sent and received. Here are personal and/or business or official letters from Franklin D. Roosevelt, James A. Farley, Harold L. Ickes, Henry M. Jackson, Warren G. Magnusson, William L. La Follette, William O. Douglas, Hamilton Fish, Albert Gore, Walt Disney, Henry Dvorshak, Estes Kefauver, Clarence C. Dill, Sam Rayburn, John W. McCormack, Clarence D. Martin, Adlai E. Stevenson, Linus Pauling, Roland H. Hartley, Robert Ripley, Ted Malone, and others; Speech and lecture manuscripts; Miscellaneous newspaper and magazine clippings that served as a source-file for speeches and writings; Newsletters and press releases while a member of Congress; Pamphlets relating to scenic, economic, and agricultural Washington State and the Columbia River Project; Campaign and personal newspaper clippings; Pictures, both personal and official; and Miscellaneous items, including a manuscript of an extended essay entitled "Why I Broke with Roosevelt."
The content of containers numbered 1 through 8 consists of correspondence, speech and lecture manuscripts and outlines, and "Letters to the Editor" interfiled and arranged chronologically by years. The content of the remaining containers is described for each.
This collection is open for research use.
The papers of Knute Hill, Representative in Congress from the 4th District of the State of Washington, were given in part to the Washington State University Library in 1961-1962 by Mr. Hill. The remainder was received in 1965 after probate of his estate.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Hill, Knute, 1876-1963 --Archives
Columbia Basin Project (U.S.); United States. President (1933-1945: Roosevelt); United States. Congress. House; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945 -- Sources
Grand Coulee Dam (Wash.)--Archives
Irrigation; Government and Politics; Washington (State)
Legislators--United States--Correspondence; Legislators--United States--Archives
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Correspondence; Speech and lecture manuscripts and outlines; and "Letters to the Editor"
  - 1909-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1939 (Box 3)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 5)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 7)
  - 1950-1963 (Box 8)
- Newsletters and Press Releases, 1939-1940 (Box 9)
- Newspaper clippings and Campaign Materials (Box 10)
- Radio Scripts, 1944-1945 (Box 11-12)
- Grand Coulee pamphlets and materials (Box 13)
- Washington State and Pacific Northwest pamphlets and materials (Box 14)
- Picture file (Box 15)
- "Why I Broke with Roosevelt" and miscellaneous (Box 16)